[SPEAKER_01]: Here's another question.
[SPEAKER_01]: I've been trying to find satisfaction through connection and a sense of belonging within the saṅgha community.
[SPEAKER_01]: However, I'm realizing that because any human group is inherently subject to shifting dynamics, comings and goings, and impermanence, resting my internal sense of safety on others leaves me feeling quite vulnerable.
[SPEAKER_01]: If the fundamental nature of all social groups is change, how can I truly take the Saṅgha as a refuge?
[SPEAKER_01]: And there's a...
[SPEAKER_01]: I thought I'd add this Sutta verse, a short verse.
[SPEAKER_01]: It says, dwell with yourselves as an island, with yourselves as a refuge, and with no other refuge.
[SPEAKER_01]: Dwell with the dhamma as an island, with the dhamma as a refuge, with no other refuge.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there is the, you know, I take refuge in the saṅgha.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but I think that has been sort of... unintentionally bastardized over centuries.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I think the answer to this question is quite simple.
[SPEAKER_00]: To that question is quite simple.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just need to upgrade your definition of saṅgha.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not a bunch of people that come together for the same purpose or cause and feel part of a unity or a group.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's literally saṅgha is people that understood the Buddha's teachings, so sotāpānas are higher.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what saṅgha is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when people take refuge in saṅgha, they take the refuge in the values that those people developed.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in, like, I take refuge in those that did the work that the Buddha outlined as something so that I can strive towards that and become part of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in, do the work myself.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what it's like.
[SPEAKER_00]: In that sutta, I think it was about when all those arahants came together, or maybe it wasn't that sutta, but it was when the Buddha was saying that the greatest assembly is the assembly of arahants.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you realize it's because it's not an assembly.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a collection of fully purified individuals.
[SPEAKER_00]: Fully an island to themselves.
[SPEAKER_00]: They don't need even the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_00]: They can't even need the Buddha anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: Fully enclosed within their understanding, purified on account of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: When those individuals come together, that's the greatest saṅgha, the greatest assembly.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's kind of the irony of it, because they're not there as a group.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're not there together.
[SPEAKER_00]: They do not partake in each other's comforts, of each other's company, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: All of that's been cleansed away from the being, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, taking the refuge in saṅgha means taking the refuge in possibility of succeeding in the training like others before you.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it doesn't mean just joining a local Buddhist group and feeling good in the company of others, like-minded people or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, for that, you don't need the Buddhist teaching.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just get into arts and crafts and join appropriate groups and you'll feel the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's the same thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Take refuge in the saṅgha means take refuge in the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, taking refuge in the Buddha means taking refuge in the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: Taking refuge in the dhamma means taking refuge in the saṅgha, i.e.
[SPEAKER_00]: those who have actually developed the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's what saṅgha is.
[SPEAKER_00]: But yes, you have the...
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, conventional now, you know, basically monks culturally ordain.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there is no like dhamma to begin with, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just do your service duties, part of the whole setup.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, people who are like formally admitted to the order are called saṅgha.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, again, you can have the saṅgha of thousands of monks.
[SPEAKER_00]: If not single one of them is even a sotāpanna, that's not a saṅgha.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just a bunch of householders that wear robes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And just like the idea that a... being part of a community with the same interests and so on, is going to somehow satisfy you or make... make you better.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's, you know, free you from suffering, if it's a Buddhist group.
[SPEAKER_00]: I suppose it can make you better.
[SPEAKER_00]: If if you yourself were unrestrained before, had no sense of moderation or the precepts, and then you join a group that installs those values.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not like there is no conventional benefit, but that's not really what the question was referring to.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was referring to that kind of emotional safety you find in the comfort of like-minded people.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's like, you might not help, you might not be able to help, but feel like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you certainly need to recognize it as a trap and as an obstacle to the actual understanding of the dhamma, because, like, how can you expect to be independent, imperturbable, immovable by the worldly winds and the big pressures and emotional discomforts and the extents of the citta it can take against you, if you still can't even contain and overcome
[SPEAKER_00]: You're quite superficially dependent on the presence of other people, because they make me feel safe.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because these ideas are the same, and we partake, we share the common goal, and it feels uplifted.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, you might feel uplifted, but you shouldn't just take it at face value and follow it blindly as some sort of positive thing, because, as I said, it's actually more often than not an obstacle to the practice, which means it's unbeneficial for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, again, you're using it to avoid the weight of the practice being felt by you alone.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's kind of a necessary precondition, really, for successful practice, is recognizing that you are alone.
[SPEAKER_00]: That nobody can do this for you, and nobody can prevent you from doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nobody can come in between you and the dhamma practice you've done successfully.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why it can't be taken away.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why it's unsurpassed, unshakable, irreversible freedom.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't depend on anything external, including chief of... among which is the other people, really.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like you're the one carrying the burden.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're the one that has to put it down.
[SPEAKER_01]: No one else can put it down for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not necessarily like, I must now say no to all the groups and never talk to people.
[SPEAKER_00]: Some people might kind of go the other way too much.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, no, you need to learn, you recognize the objective need to collect the right information, right values, learn about the right direction of practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: And for that, well, directly or indirectly, you need an instruction of another.
[SPEAKER_00]: Either through reading the suttas, watching the talks, or if you have access to those people, talking to them directly and learning from it, but not so that you can feel safe in their company, but so that you can then, when you are alone, and when eventually you are alone, or even before that, so you can start taking it on upon yourself to practice rightly, regardless of whether there are others supporting or not, whether there is a group or not, whether you feel alone or lonely, it doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: The practice remains the same and unchanged.